`Steve K K Kenei P.O. Box 21727-00505

Nairobi, Kenya

Email: stevekenei@gmail.com

kenei.steve@redcross.or.ke

Mobile contacts: +254780899218

+254774899218

Profile

I am a data savvy researcher with nine years of professional experience in the fields of open data, poverty research, humanitarian assistance, domestic spending, foreign aid analysis, and promoting the use of evidence by government policy makers. I have acquired extensive skills and experience in conducting quantitative and qualitative research and developing of data visualisation tools and policy briefs. I am also experienced in developing and conducting capacity building activities.

My most recent role as a Data Analyst at the International Center for Humanitarian Affairs involves developing and implementing data preparedness modules for operations across the Kenya Red Cross, paying an important emphasis on work around Forecast Based Financing (FbF) and Forecast Based Action (FbA), previously as a Data Scientist at Development Initiatives (DI) Africa Hub-based in Nairobi, I had the overall responsibility in data curation for the delivery of high quality data tools, research and analytical work for DI Africa Hub. This role involved working with a team of data analysts and scientists to ensure project delivery to the highest standards.

I am an avid reader in diverse themes of global politics, governance and development, and science and technology. I am also a team player, proactive and of high integrity. I am able to work independently to ensure that deadlines are met, in addition, I am agile and able to prioritise work to ensure that targets are met. My experience has increasingly led me to build my skills in establishing and managing partnerships and turning them to results.

Qualifications

Bachelor of Science Mathematics (Applied Mathematics),NAIROBINairobi University, School of Mathematics2004-2010Master of Science (Health Informatics)NAIROBIMoi University2019 -

Professional Experience

INTERNATIONAL CENTER FOR HUMANITRIAN AFFAIRS: DATA ANALYST

Role: Data curation, data visualisation, research writing and project management.

 Understand information needs of the Kenya Red Cross Society and the regional National Societies decision makers and translate these into data analysis and information products. NOV 2018 -PRESENT

- Developing data models for data intensive projects, applying standards where possible.
- Supporting Kenya Red Cross Society and regional National Societies in using the products, maps, and visualizations provided by the team.
- Review of available open and closed (secondary) data sources for use instead
 of collecting new data.
- Review and cleaning of data.
- Analysis of data, both small and big. Development of algorithms to combine and analyse these data.
- Support and guide students and volunteers that work in the team on data analysis.

DEVELOPMENT INITIATIVES: DATA SCIENTIST

JAN 2016 -MAY 2018

Role: Data curation, capacity building, project management, report writing, data visualisation and ICT infrastructure management.

- Developed research methodology on a development data audit for Kenya, Uganda and Nepal. Providing a detailed look at existing data official and non official data sources at country level aimed at providing a holistic picture of current and potential data sources to be used in tracking implementation and tracking of the 2030 agenda.
- Researched on the impact of Citizen Generated Data (CGD) on educational outcomes following the roll out of free primary education in Kenya
- Developed survey instruments anchored in the SDG indicator frameworks for a mini census in Nakuru County and for a ten-country research work on SDG monitoring and perception led by African Monitor
- As part of the Leave No One Behind (LNOB) agenda, I was responsible for developing country profiles and provided narratives on the status of poverty and socio-economic outcomes for groups likely to be left behind. I was also a contributing author/editor of the CSO lead SDG Annex to Kenya's Voluntary National Report on country status on SDGs presented by the Government at the last High-Level Forum in New York
- Led engagements at the Africa Hub on the Data Revolution debate which led
 me to contribute to the <u>UNECA Data Revolution Report</u> and co-wrote the
 Global Open Data for Agriculture and Nutrition (GODAN) SDG2 Accountability
 Framework report. This role also has me initiating and maintaining key
 relationships with key government offices at both the national and sub
 national level, CSOs and KNBS.
- Led a team of interns and data scientists in the development of the Spotlight on <u>Kenya</u> and <u>Uganda</u>, an online visualisation portal that highlights sub national disparities in poverty distribution among other relevant socioeconomic indicators alongside sector spending at county level.
- Head of Africa IT function

DEVELOPMENT INITIATIVES: TECHNICAL ANALYST

MAR2013 - DEC 2015

Role: Institutional capacity building, data curation, project management, report writing, data visualisation and ICT infrastructure management.

- As Country lead for the <u>International Aid Transparency Initiative</u>, I was responsible for developing the country roll out strategy for support to local organisations to publish to the standard. Its implementation had me develop training modules for local CSOs to equip them with the capacity to publish financial information to the standard. This included supporting the Kenya Red Cross.
- Supported the Capacity Development Manager to design and implement tailored capacity support and mentoring for CSOs to better access, analyse, and use information to advocate for better resource allocation and service delivery in key sectors of health, education, and agriculture, among others
- Developed research methodology, conducted research and contributed to analytical writing of DI reports while also developing innovative data and concept visualisations for all the Africa Hub reports and methodology mapping
- Worked with Manor House Agricultural School in Kitale to develop an SMS based information dissemination system to sensitise local farmers on farming methods to improve yields. This had me develop technical specification documentation for the program
- I was chosen as the staff representative for the Africa Hub and was tasked with liaising staff welfare matters with the head office

DEVELOPMENT INITIATIVES: RESEARCH AND IT INTERN

Role: Data collection, entry, cleaning and analysing and; ICT management

MAR - DEC 2012

- Conducted research and wrote two papers on open data and natural resources in East Africa
- Contributed to analysis on Malawi for the Investments to End Poverty (ITEP) report published in 2013
- Participated in agenda setting and report formulation for the Chronic Poverty Advisory Network (CPAN)
- Setup, ran and serviced/maintained the office IT infrastructure in a multicultural organisation (multinational and ethnic)
- Through research, found and shared articles on poverty on the offices knowledge platform and maintained the newspaper library

KENYA NATIONAL EXAMINATION COUNCIL (KNEC)

DECEMBER 2011

I was an assistant team leader at the data capture centre and acted as the liaison between examiners and clerks throughout examination marking period to ensure timely capture of data and release of reports to examiners. I also offered IT support and had the role of conflict resolution between data capturers and examiners

CFC STANBIC BANK: INTERN AUG-NOV 2009

I was responsible for the branch's Know Your Customer cases and interacted with customers regularly. I also offered minor IT support

ELECTORAL COMMISSION OF KENYA: REGISTRATION CLERK

AUG-SEPT

Registration of voters for the 2005 referendum and 2007 general election, also engaged **2005 & 2007** a great deal in civic education on the voting process.

Personality profile

https://app.plum.io/profile/4e293a497a50e036e257e19894d61e3ad7f71e17

Professional training

- Forcecast Based Financing, Nairobi, SHEAR
- GIS use, 2018, Airbus Foundation
- Big Data Use, 2017 UN Staff college
- IATI XML Schema, Manchester, England, 2013
- Project Management Training, iHub, Nairobi, 2012
- Data analysis management and reporting, In-depth Research Services Nairobi Kenya, 2012
- Data Capture, KNEC, Nairobi, December 2011

Technical skills

- Good proficiency using R and Python programming languages with basic programming skills in HTML, CSS and PHP
- Expert proficiency in using QGIS for GIS visualisation
- Networking and server management (SBS 2011)
- Advance visualisation skills using Power BI and Tabula
- Advanced data mining skills using Tabula and Trifacta among other software
- Advanced skills in Outlook, Excel, Word and PowerPoint
- Basic skills in Access, Wordpress and Microsoft Projects
- Intermediate level STATA skills

Selected papers/publications

- A Collaborative Process towards a SDG2 Accountability Framework, Andre Laperriere, Sylvia Szabo, Gawain Kripke, Jay Bhalla, Steve Kenei, Ammad Bahalim and Livia Bizikova (2017)
- <u>Citizen-generated data and sustainable development: evidence from case studies in Kenya and</u> Uganda, Rebecca, Ssanyu; Rono-Bett, Karen; Kenei, Steve (Development Initiatives, 2017-03)

- Voluntary National Review (VNR) Of Progress on SDGs In Kenya, Various (2017)
- Global Humanitarian Assistance Report 2016, Development Initiatives
- <u>East Africa's emerging natural resource revenues and what it means for the region's poorest,</u> Development Initiatives, 2012, Steve Kenei
- Open data: Learnings from the Kenya Open Data Initiative (KODI) for CSOs, Development Initiative, 2012, Steve Kenei

Volunteer experience

- Data Scientist working with the Elgeyo Marakwet County in development of a crop census (June 2018-Presently)
- Taught high school Physics, Chemistry, Biology and Computer Science the ROCK Center in Kibera (2014-15)
- Taught high school Chemistry, Neema Childrens Home, 2003

Referees

Dr Halima Saado Abdilahia, Research and Learning Coordinator, International Center for Humanitarian Affairs, +254710315830, saado.halima@redcross.or.ke

Karen Rono-Bett, Regional Technical Lead, Development Initiatives, +254721403666 ronokaren@gmail.com

Jason Braganza, Deputy Executive Director, Tax Justice Network Alliance Africa, +254717471062 jason.rosario.braganza@gmail.com

Davis Adieno, Africa Regional Manager at Global Partnership for Sustainable Development Data (GPSDD), +254726325429 davis.adieno@yahoo.com